[{"raw_text": "Space Exploration Technologies Corp. , more commonly known as SpaceX , is a private American aerospace company and space transportation company headquartered at the Starbase development site in Starbase , Texas . Since its founding in 2002 , the company has made numerous advances in rocket propulsion , reusable launch vehicles , human spaceflight and satellite constellation technology . As of 2025[update ] , SpaceX is the world 's dominant space launch provider , its launch cadence eclipsing all others , including private competitors and national programs like the Chinese space program . SpaceX , NASA , and the United States Armed Forces work closely together by means of governmental contracts .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "SpaceX was founded by Elon Musk in 2002 with a vision of decreasing the costs of space launches , paving the way to a self - sustaining colony on Mars . In 2008 , Falcon 1 successfully launched into orbit after three failed launch attempts . The company then moved towards the development of the larger Falcon 9 rocket and the Dragon 1 capsule to satisfy NASA 's COTS contracts for deliveries to the International Space Station . By 2012 , SpaceX finished all COTS test flights and began delivering Commercial Resupply Services missions to the International Space Station . Also around that time , SpaceX started developing hardware to make the Falcon 9 first stage reusable . The company demonstrated the first successful first - stage landing in 2015 and re - launch of the first stage in 2017 . Falcon Heavy , built from three Falcon 9 boosters , first flew in 2018 after a more than decade - long development process . As of May 2025 , the company 's Falcon 9 rockets have landed and flown again more than 450 times , reaching 1–3 launches a week .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "These milestones delivered the company much - needed investment and SpaceX sought to diversify its sources of income . In 2019 , the first operational satellite of the Starlink internet satellite constellation came online . In subsequent years , Starlink generated the bulk of SpaceX 's income and paved the way for its Starshield military counterpart . In 2020 , SpaceX began to operate its Dragon 2 capsules to deliver crewed missions for NASA and private entities . Around this time , SpaceX began building test prototypes for Starship , which is the largest launch vehicle in history and aims to fully realize the company 's vision of a fully reusable , cost - effective and adaptable launch vehicle . SpaceX is also developing its own space suit and astronaut via its Polaris program as well as developing the human lander for lunar missions under NASA 's Artemis program . SpaceX is not publicly traded ; a space industry newspaper estimated that SpaceX has a revenue of over $ 10 billion in 2024 .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In early 2001 , Elon Musk met Robert Zubrin and donated $ 100,000 to his Mars Society , joining its board of directors for a short time . : 30–31 He gave a plenary talk at their fourth convention where he announced Mars Oasis , a project to land a greenhouse and grow plants on Mars . Musk initially attempted to acquire a Dnepr launch vehicle for the project through Russian contacts from Jim Cantrell .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Musk returned with his team to Moscow , this time bringing Michael Griffin , who later became the 11th Administrator of NASA , but found the Russians increasingly unreceptive . On the flight home , Musk announced he could start a company to build the affordable rockets they needed instead . By applying vertical integration , using inexpensive commercial off - the - shelf components when possible , and adopting the modular approach of modern software engineering , Musk believed SpaceX could significantly cut launch costs .", "gold_annotations": ["B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In early 2002 , Elon Musk started to look for staff for his company , soon to be named SpaceX. Musk approached five people for the initial positions at the fledgling company , including Griffin , who declined the position of Chief Engineer , : 11 Jim Cantrell and John Garvey ( Cantrell and Garvey later founded the company Vector Launch ) , rocket engineer Tom Mueller , and Chris Thompson . SpaceX was first headquartered in a warehouse in El Segundo , California . Early SpaceX employees , such as Tom Mueller ( CTO ) , Gwynne Shotwell ( COO ) , and Chris Thompson ( VP of Operations ) , came from neighboring TRW and Boeing corporations . By November 2005 , the company had 160 employees . Musk personally interviewed and approved all of SpaceX 's early employees . : 22", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Musk has stated that one of his goals with SpaceX is to decrease the cost and improve the reliability of access to space , ultimately by a factor of ten .", "gold_annotations": ["B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "SpaceX developed its first orbital launch vehicle , the Falcon 1 , with internal funding . The Falcon 1 was an expendable two - stage - to - orbit small - lift launch vehicle . The total development cost of Falcon 1 was approximately $ 90 million to $ 100 million . : 215", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The Falcon rocket series was named after Star Wars 's Millennium Falcon fictional spacecraft .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In 2004 , SpaceX protested against NASA to the Government Accountability Office ( GAO ) because of a sole - source contract awarded to Kistler Aerospace . Before the GAO could respond , NASA withdrew the contract , and formed the COTS program . : 109–110 In 2005 , SpaceX announced plans to pursue a human - rated commercial space program through the end of the decade , a program that would later become the Dragon spacecraft . In 2006 , the company was selected by NASA and awarded $ 396 million to provide crew and cargo resupply demonstration contracts to the International Space Station ( ISS ) under the COTS program .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The first two Falcon 1 launches were purchased by the United States Department of Defense under the DARPA Falcon Project which evaluated new U.S. launch vehicles suitable for use in hypersonic missile delivery for Prompt Global Strike . The first three launches of the rocket , between 2006 and 2008 , all resulted in failures , which almost ended the company . Financing for Tesla Motors had failed , as well , and consequently Tesla , SolarCity , and Musk personally were all nearly bankrupt at the same time . : 178–182 Musk was reportedly \" waking from nightmares , screaming and in physical pain \" because of the stress . : 216", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The financial situation started to turn around with the first successful launch achieved on the fourth attempt on September 28 , 2008 . Musk split his remaining $ 30 million between SpaceX and Tesla , and NASA awarded the first Commercial Resupply Services ( CRS ) contract awarding $ 1.6 billion to SpaceX in December , thus financially saving the company . : 217–221 Based on these factors and the further business operations they enabled , the Falcon 1 was soon retired following its second successful , and fifth total , launch in July 2009 . This allowed SpaceX to focus company resources on the development of a larger orbital rocket , the Falcon 9 . Gwynne Shotwell was also promoted to company president at the time , for her role in successfully negotiating the CRS contract with the NASA Associate Administrator Bill Gerstenmaier . : 222", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "SpaceX originally intended to follow its light Falcon 1 launch vehicle with an intermediate capacity vehicle , the Falcon 5 . The company instead decided in 2005 to proceed with the development of the Falcon 9 , a reusable heavier lift vehicle . Development of the Falcon 9 was accelerated by NASA , which committed to purchasing several commercial flights if specific capabilities were demonstrated . This started with seed money from the Commercial Orbital Transportation Services ( COTS ) program in 2006 . The overall contract award was $ 278 million to provide development funding for the Dragon spacecraft , Falcon 9 , and demonstration launches of Falcon 9 with Dragon . As part of this contract , the Falcon 9 launched for the first time in June 2010 with the Dragon Spacecraft Qualification Unit , using a mockup of the Dragon spacecraft .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The first operational Dragon spacecraft was launched in December 2010 aboard COTS Demo Flight 1 , the Falcon 9 's second flight , and safely returned to Earth after two orbits , completing all its mission objectives . By December 2010 , the SpaceX production line was manufacturing one Falcon 9 and Dragon every three months .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In April 2011 , as part of its second - round Commercial Crew Development ( CCDev ) program , NASA issued a $ 75 million contract for SpaceX to develop an integrated launch escape system for Dragon in preparation for human - rating it as a crew transport vehicle to the ISS . NASA awarded SpaceX a fixed - price Space Act Agreement ( SAA ) to produce a detailed design of the crew transportation system in August 2012 .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In early 2012 , approximately two - thirds of SpaceX stock was owned by Musk and his seventy million shares were then estimated to be worth $ 875 million on private markets , valuing SpaceX at $ 1.3 billion . In May 2012 , with the Dragon C2 + launch , Dragon became the first commercial spacecraft to deliver cargo to the International Space Station . After the flight , the company private equity valuation nearly doubled to $ 2.4 billion or $ 20 / share . By that time , SpaceX had operated on total funding of approximately $ 1 billion over its first decade of operation . Of this , private equity provided approximately $ 200 million , with Musk investing approximately $ 100 million and other investors having put in about $ 100 million .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "SpaceX 's active reusability test program began in late 2012 with testing low - altitude , low - speed aspects of the landing technology . The Falcon 9 prototypes performed vertical takeoffs and landings ( VTOL ) . High - velocity , high - altitude tests of the booster atmospheric return technology began in late 2013 .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "SpaceX launched the first commercial mission for a private customer in 2013 . In 2014 , SpaceX won nine contracts out of the 20 that were openly competed worldwide . That year Arianespace requested that European governments provide additional subsidies to face the competition from SpaceX. Beginning in 2014 , SpaceX capabilities and pricing also began to affect the market for launch of U.S. military payloads , which for nearly a decade had been dominated by the large U.S. launch provider United Launch Alliance ( ULA ) . The monopoly had allowed launch costs by the U.S. provider to rise to over $ 400 million over the years . In September 2014 , NASA 's Director of Commercial Spaceflight , Kevin Crigler , awarded SpaceX the Commercial Crew Transportation Capability ( CCtCap ) contract to finalize the development of the Crew Transportation System . The contract included several technical and certification milestones , an uncrewed flight test , a crewed flight test , and six operational missions after certification .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In January 2015 , SpaceX raised $ 1 billion in funding from Google and Fidelity Investments , in exchange for 8.33 % of the company , establishing the company valuation at approximately $ 12 billion . The same month SpaceX announced the development of a new satellite constellation , called Starlink , to provide global broadband internet service with 4,000 satellites .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The Falcon 9 had its first major failure in late June 2015 , when the seventh ISS resupply mission , CRS-7 exploded two minutes into the flight . The problem was traced to a failed two - foot - long steel strut that held a helium pressure vessel , which broke free due to the force of acceleration . This caused a breach and allowed high - pressure helium to escape into the low - pressure propellant tank , causing the failure .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The 2024 Summer Olympics ( French : Les Jeux Olympiques d'été de 2024 ) , officially the Games of the XXXIII Olympiad ( French : Jeux de la XXXIIIe olympiade de l'ère moderne ) and branded as Paris 2024 , were an international multi - sport event held in France from 26 July to 11 August 2024 , with several events starting from 24 July . Paris was the host city , with events ( mainly football ) held in 16 additional cities in metropolitan France , including the sailing centre in the second - largest city of France , Marseille , on the Mediterranean Sea , as well as one subsite for surfing in Tahiti , French Polynesia .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Paris was awarded the Games at the 131st IOC Session in Lima , Peru , on 13 September 2017 . After multiple withdrawals that left only Paris and Los Angeles in contention , the International Olympic Committee ( IOC ) approved a process to concurrently award the 2024 and 2028 Summer Olympics to the two remaining candidate cities ; both bids were praised for their high technical plans and innovative ways to use a record - breaking number of existing and temporary facilities . Having previously hosted in 1900 and 1924 , Paris became the second city ever to host the Summer Olympics three times ( after London , which hosted the games in 1908 , 1948 , and 2012 ) . Paris 2024 marked the centenary of the 1924 games and the 1924 Winter Olympics in Chamonix ( the first Winter Olympics ) , as well as the sixth Olympic Games hosted by France ( three Summer Olympics and three Winter Olympics ) and the first with this distinction since the 1992 Winter Games in Albertville . The Summer Games returned to the traditional four - year Olympiad cycle , after the 2020 edition was postponed to 2021 due to the COVID-19 pandemic .", "gold_annotations": ["B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Paris 2024 featured the debut of breaking as an Olympic sport , and was the final Olympic Games held during the IOC presidency of Thomas Bach . The 2024 Games were expected to cost € 9 billion . The opening ceremony was held outside of a stadium for the first time in modern Olympic history , being outdoors in the Paris 's downtown and with as athletes were paraded by boat along the Seine . Paris 2024 was the first Olympics in history to reach full gender parity on the field of play , with equal numbers of male and female athletes .", "gold_annotations": ["B-LOC", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The United States topped the medal table for the fourth consecutive Summer Games and 19th time overall , with 40 gold and 126 total medals . China tied with the United States on gold ( 40 ) , but finished second due to having fewer silvers ; the nation won 91 medals overall . This was the first time a gold medal tie had occurred between the two most successful nations in Summer Olympic history . Japan finished third with 20 gold and 45 total medals , and sixth in the overall medal count . Australia finished fourth with 18 gold and 53 total medals , marking the nation 's most successful Summer Olympics of all time , and fifth in the overall medal count . The host nation , France , finished fifth with 16 gold and 64 total medals , marking their first top - five finish since the 1996 Summer Olympics , and fourth in the overall medal count . Dominica , Saint Lucia , Cape Verde and Albania won their first - ever Olympic medals , the former two both being gold , with Botswana and Guatemala also winning their first - ever gold medals . The Refugee Olympic Team also won their first - ever medal , Cindy Ngamba , a refugee from Cameroon , winning a bronze in boxing .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Despite some controversies throughout relating to politics , logistics and conditions in the Olympic Village , the games were considered a success by the press , Parisians and observers upon its conclusion.[a ] The Paris Olympics broke all - time records for ticket sales , with more than 9.5 million tickets sold ( 12.1 million including the Paralympic Games ) .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Having previously hosted the 1900 and 1924 Games , Paris did not attempt to host the Olympics again until it bid , unsuccessfully , for the 1992 Games which were awarded to Barcelona . Subsequent bids for the 2008 and 2012 Games were also unsuccessful , as they were awarded to Beijing and London , respectively . Undeterred , Paris decided to bid once more for the 2024 edition , which would mark the centenary of its last Games .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The six candidate cities were Paris , Hamburg , Boston , Budapest , Rome , and Los Angeles . The bidding process was slowed by withdrawals , political uncertainty , and rising costs . Boston surpassed Los Angeles , San Francisco , and Washington , DC , for the official U.S. bid . On 27 July 2015 , Boston and the USOC mutually agreed to terminate Boston 's bid to host the Games , partly because of mixed feelings among city residents . Hamburg withdrew its bid on 29 November 2015 after holding a referendum . Rome withdrew on 21 September 2016 , citing fiscal difficulties . Budapest withdrew on 22 February 2017 , after a petition against the bid collected more signatures than necessary for a referendum .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Following these withdrawals , the IOC Executive Board met on 9 June 2017 in Lausanne , Switzerland , to discuss the 2024 and 2028 bid processes . The International Olympic Committee formally proposed electing the 2024 and 2028 Olympic host cities at the same time , a proposal which an Extraordinary IOC Session approved on 11 July 2017 in Lausanne . The IOC set up a process whereby the LA 2024 and Paris 2024 bid committees met with the IOC to discuss which city would host the Games in 2024 and 2028 and whether it was possible to select the host cities for both at the same time .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Following the decision to award the two Games simultaneously , Paris was understood to be the preferred host for 2024 . On 31 July 2017 , the IOC announced Los Angeles as the sole candidate for 2028 , enabling Paris to be confirmed as host for 2024 . Both decisions were ratified at the 131st IOC Session on 13 September 2017 .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Paris was elected as the host city on 13 September 2017 at the 131st IOC Session in Lima , Peru . The two French IOC members , Guy Drut and Tony Estanguet , were ineligible to vote under the rules of the Olympic Charter .", "gold_annotations": ["B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Most of the Olympic events were held in the city of Paris and its metropolitan region , including the neighbouring cities of Saint - Denis , Le Bourget , Nanterre , Versailles , and Vaires - sur - Marne .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The basketball preliminaries and handball finals were held in Lille , 225 km ( 140 mi ) from the host city , Paris ; the sailing and some of the football games were held in the Mediterranean city of Marseille , which is 777 km ( 483 mi ) from Paris ; meanwhile , the surfing events were held in Teahupo'o village in the overseas territory of Tahiti , French Polynesia , which is 15,716 km ( 9,765 mi ) from Paris . Football was also hosted in an additional five cities : Bordeaux , Décines - Charpieu ( Lyon ) , Nantes , Nice and Saint - Étienne , some of which are home to Ligue 1 clubs .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The president of the Paris 2024 Olympic Organizing Committee , Tony Estanguet , unveiled the Olympic and Paralympic medals for the Games in February 2024 , which on the obverse featured embedded hexagon - shaped tokens of scrap iron that had been taken from the original construction of the Eiffel Tower , with the logo of the Games engraved into it . Approximately 5,084 medals would be produced by the French mint Monnaie de Paris , and were designed by Chaumet , a luxury jewellery firm based in Paris .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The reverse of the medals features Nike , the Greek goddess of victory , inside the Panathenaic Stadium which hosted the first modern Olympics in 1896 . Parthenon and the Eiffel Tower can also be seen in the background on both sides of the medal . Each medal weighs 455–529 g ( 16–19 oz ) , has a diameter of 85 mm ( 3.3 in ) and is 9.2 mm ( 0.36 in ) thick . The gold medals are made with 98.8 percent silver and 1.13 percent gold , while the bronze medals are made up with copper , zinc , and tin .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "France reached an agreement with Europol and the UK Home Office to help strengthen security and \" facilitate operational information exchange and international law enforcement cooperation \" during the Games . The agreement included a plan to deploy more drones and sea barriers to prevent small boats from crossing the Channel illegally . The British Army would also provide support by deploying Starstreak surface - to - air missile units for air security . To prepare for the Games , the Paris police held inspections and rehearsals in their bomb disposal unit , similar to their preparations for the 2023 Rugby World Cup at the Stade de France .", "gold_annotations": ["B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "As part of a visit to France by Qatari Emir Sheikh Tamim bin Hamad Al - Thani , several agreements were signed between the two nations to enhance security for the Olympics . In preparation for the significant security demands and counterterrorism measures , Poland pledged to contribute security troops , including sniffer dog handlers , to support international efforts aimed at ensuring the safety of the Games . The Qatari Minister of Interior and Commander of Lekhwiya ( the Qatari security forces ) convened a meeting on 3 April 2024 to discuss security operations ahead of the Olympics , with officials and security leaders in attendance , including Nasser Al - Khelaifi and Sheikh Jassim bin Mansour Al Thani . A week before the opening ceremony , the Lekhwiya were reported to have been deployed in Paris on 16 July 2024 .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In the weeks running up to the opening of the Olympics , it was reported that police officers would be deployed from Belgium , Brazil , Canada ( through the RCMP / OPS / CPS / SQ ) , Cyprus , the Czech Republic , Denmark , Estonia , Finland , Germany ( through Bundespolizei / NRW Police ) , India , Ireland , Italy , Luxembourg , Morocco , Netherlands , Norway , Poland , Portugal , Slovakia , South Korea , Spain ( through the CNP / GC ) , Sweden , the UAE , the UK , and the US ( through the LAPD , LASD , NYPD , and the Fairfax County , Virginia , Police Department ) , with more than 40 countries providing police assistance to their French counterparts .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Security concerns impacted the plans that had been announced for the opening ceremony , which was to take place as a public event along the Seine ; the expected attendance was reduced by half from an estimated 600,000 to 300,000 , with plans for free viewing locations now being by invitation only . In April 2024 , after Islamic State claimed responsibility for the Crocus City Hall attack in March , and made several threats against the UEFA Champions League quarter - finals , French president Emmanuel Macron indicated that the opening ceremony could be scaled back or re - located if necessary . French authorities had placed roughly 75,000 police and military officials on the streets of Paris in the lead - up to the Games .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Following the end of the Games , the national counterterrorism prosecutor , Olivier Christen , revealed that French authorities foiled three terror plots meant to attack the Olympic and Paralympic Games , resulting in the arrest of five suspects .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "To reduce the environmental impact and climate footprint of the Games , the Olympic venues served twice as much plant - based food as was available in London in 2012 and Rio in 2016 . Vegan chicken nuggets and vegan hot dogs were served in place of the meat - based variety . Venues for spectators served on average two - thirds plant - based meals . The Place de la Concorde , the venue that hosted the skateboarding , breakdancing and BMX events , only served plant - based food . The football stadiums served 40 % plant - based food . About 30 % of the meals served to athletes in the Olympic Village were plant - based .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Apple Inc. is an American multinational technology company headquartered in Cupertino , California , in Silicon Valley , best known for its consumer electronics , software and online services . Founded in 1976 as Apple Computer Company by Steve Jobs , Steve Wozniak and Ronald Wayne , the company was incorporated by Jobs and Wozniak as Apple Computer , Inc. the following year . It was renamed to its current name in 2007 as the company had expanded its focus from computers to consumer electronics . Apple has been described as a Big Tech company .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The company was founded to market Wozniak 's Apple I personal computer . Its successor , the Apple II , became one of the first successful mass - produced microcomputers . Apple introduced the Lisa in 1983 and the Macintosh in 1984 as some of the first computers to use a graphical user interface and a mouse . By 1985 , internal conflicts led to Jobs leaving the company to form NeXT and Wozniak withdrawing to other ventures ; John Sculley served as CEO for over a decade . In the 1990s , Apple lost considerable market share in the personal computer industry to the lower - priced Wintel duopoly of Intel - powered PC clones running Microsoft Windows , and neared bankruptcy by 1997 . To overhaul its market strategy , it acquired NeXT , bringing Jobs back to the company . Under his leadership , Apple returned to profitability by introducing the iMac , iPod , iPhone , and iPad devices ; creating the iTunes Store ; launching the \" Think different \" advertising campaign ; and opening the Apple Store retail chain . Jobs resigned in 2011 for health reasons , and died two months later ; he was succeeded as CEO by Tim Cook .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Apple 's product lineup includes portable and home hardware like the iPhone , iPad , Apple Watch , Mac , and Apple TV ; several in - house operating systems such as iOS , iPadOS , and macOS ; and various software and services including Apple Pay and iCloud , as well as multimedia streaming services like Apple Music and Apple TV . Since 2011 , Apple has for the most part been the world 's largest company by market capitalization , and , as of 2024[update ] , is the largest manufacturing company by revenue , the fourth - largest personal computer vendor , the largest vendor of tablet computers , and the largest vendor of mobile phones . Apple became the first publicly traded US company to be valued at over $ 1 trillion in 2018 , and , as of October 2025[update ] , is valued at just over $ 4 trillion .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Apple has received criticism regarding its contractors ' labor conditions , its relationship with trade unions , its environmental practices , and its corporate ethics , including anti - competitive tactics , materials sourcing , and its acquisitions of smaller businesses . Nevertheless , the company has a large following and enjoys a high level of customer loyalty . It has consistently been ranked as one of the world 's most valuable brands since the late 2000s .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Apple Computer Company was founded on April 1 , 1976 , by Steve Jobs , Steve Wozniak , and Ronald Wayne as a partnership . The company 's first product was the Apple I , a computer designed and hand - built entirely by Wozniak . To finance its creation , Jobs sold his Volkswagen Bus , and Wozniak sold his HP-65 calculator . Neither received the full selling price but in total earned $ 1,300 ( equivalent to $ 7,200 in 2024 ) . Wozniak debuted the first prototype Apple I at the Homebrew Computer Club in July 1976 . The Apple I was sold as a motherboard with CPU , RAM , and basic textual - video chips — a base kit concept which was not yet marketed as a complete personal computer . It was priced soon after debut for $ 666.66 ( equivalent to $ 3,700 in 2024 ) . Wozniak later said he was unaware of the coincidental mark of the beast in the number 666 , and that he came up with the price because he liked \" repeating digits \" .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Apple Computer , Inc. was incorporated in Cupertino , California , on January 3 , 1977 , without Wayne , who had left and sold his share of the company back to Jobs and Wozniak for $ 800 only twelve days after having co - founded it . Multimillionaire Mike Markkula provided essential business expertise and funding of $ 250,000 ( equivalent to $ 1,297,000 in 2024 ) to Jobs and Wozniak during the incorporation of Apple . During the first five years of operations , revenue grew exponentially , doubling about every four months . Between September 1977 and September 1980 , yearly sales grew from $ 775,000 to US$ 118 million , an average annual growth rate of 533 % .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The Apple II , also designed by Wozniak , was introduced on April 16 , 1977 , at the first West Coast Computer Faire . It differs from its major rivals , the TRS-80 and Commodore PET , because of its character cell - based color graphics and open architecture . The Apple I and early Apple II models use ordinary audio cassette tapes as storage devices , which were superseded by the 5 + 1⁄4 - inch floppy disk drive and interface called the Disk II in 1978 .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The Apple II was chosen to be the desktop platform for the first killer application of the business world : VisiCalc , a spreadsheet program released in 1979 . VisiCalc created a business market for the Apple II and gave home users an additional reason to buy an Apple II : compatibility with the office , but Apple II market share remained behind home computers made by competitors such as Atari , Commodore , and Tandy .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "On December 12 , 1980 , Apple went public with an initial public offering ( IPO ) on the fully electronic Nasdaq stock market , selling 4.6 million shares at $ 22 per share ( $ .10 per share when adjusting for stock splits as of September 3 , 2022[update ] ) , generating over $ 100 million , which was more capital than any IPO since Ford Motor Company in 1956 . By the end of the day , around 300 millionaires were created , including Jobs and Wozniak , from a stock price of $ 29 per share and a market cap of $ 1.778 billion .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In November and December 1979 , Steve Jobs and Apple employees , including Jef Raskin , visited Xerox PARC , where they observed the Xerox Alto , featuring a graphical user interface ( GUI ) and a mouse . Jobs had negotiated with Xerox in advance to gain access to PARC 's technology , in exchange for the right to purchase $ 1 million worth of Apple 's pre - IPO shares . This visit influenced Jobs to implement a GUI in Apple 's products , starting with the Apple Lisa . Despite being pioneering as a mass - marketed GUI computer , the Lisa suffered from high costs and limited software options , leading to commercial failure .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Jobs , infuriated by his removal from the Lisa team , joined the company 's Macintosh division in January 1981 . Raskin had envisioned the Macintosh as a low - cost , portable computer and Wozniak had helped its development until a plane crash in early 1981 forced him to step back from the project . Wozniak 's absence allowed Jobs to quickly take over the project and he redefined the Macintosh as a graphical system that would be cheaper than the Lisa , undercutting his former division . Jobs was also hostile to the Apple II division , which at the time , generated most of the company 's revenue .", "gold_annotations": ["B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In 1984 , Apple launched the Macintosh , the first personal computer without a bundled programming language . Its debut was signified by \" 1984 \" , a US$ 1.5 - million television advertisement directed by Ridley Scott that aired during the third quarter of Super Bowl XVIII on January 22 , 1984 . This was hailed as a watershed event for Apple 's success and was called a \" masterpiece \" by CNN and one of the greatest TV advertisements of all time by TV Guide .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The advertisement created great interest in the Macintosh , and sales were initially good , but began to taper off dramatically after the first three months as reviews started to come in . Jobs had required 128 kilobytes of RAM , which limited its speed and software in favor of aspiring for a projected price point of $ 1,000 ( equivalent to $ 3,000 in 2024 ) . The Macintosh shipped for $ 2,495 ( equivalent to $ 7,600 in 2024 ) , a price panned by critics due to its slow performance . In early 1985 , this sales slump triggered a power struggle between Steve Jobs and CEO John Sculley , who had been hired away from Pepsi two years earlier by Jobs saying , \" Do you want to sell sugar water for the rest of your life or come with me and change the world ? \" Sculley removed Jobs as the head of the Macintosh division , with unanimous support from the Apple board of directors .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The board of directors instructed Sculley to contain Jobs and his ability to launch expensive forays into untested products . Rather than submit to Sculley 's direction , Jobs attempted to oust him from leadership . Jean - Louis Gassée informed Sculley that Jobs had been attempting to organize a boardroom coup , and called an emergency meeting at which Apple 's executive staff sided with Sculley , and stripped Jobs of all operational duties . Jobs resigned from Apple in September 1985 and took several Apple employees with him to found NeXT . Wozniak had also quit his active employment at Apple earlier in 1985 to pursue other ventures , expressing his frustration with Apple 's treatment of the Apple II division and stating that the company had \" been going in the wrong direction for the last five years \" . Wozniak remained employed by Apple as a representative , receiving a stipend estimated to be $ 120,000 per year . Jobs and Wozniak remained Apple shareholders following their departures .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-MONEY", "I-MONEY", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "After the departures of Jobs and Wozniak in 1985 , Sculley launched the Macintosh 512 K that year with quadruple the RAM , and introduced the LaserWriter , the first reasonably priced PostScript - based laser printer . PageMaker , an early desktop publishing application taking advantage of the PostScript language , was also released by Aldus Corporation in July 1985 . It has been suggested that the combination of Macintosh , LaserWriter , and PageMaker was responsible for the creation of the desktop publishing market .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "This dominant position in the desktop publishing market allowed the company to focus on higher price points , the so - called \" high - right policy \" named for the position on a chart of price vs. profits . Newer models selling at higher price points offered higher profit margin , and appeared to have no effect on total sales as power users snapped up every increase in speed . Although some worried about pricing themselves out of the market , the high - right policy was in full force by the mid-1980s , due to Jean - Louis Gassée 's slogan of \" fifty - five or die \" , referring to the 55 % profit margins of the Macintosh II .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "This policy began to backfire late in the decade as desktop publishing programs appeared on IBM PC compatibles with some of the same functionality of the Macintosh at far lower price points . The company lost its dominant position in the desktop publishing market and estranged many of its original consumer customer base who could no longer afford Apple products . The Christmas season of 1989 was the first in the company 's history to have declining sales , which led to a 20 % drop in Apple 's stock price . During this period , the relationship between Sculley and Gassée deteriorated , leading Sculley to effectively demote Gassée in January 1990 by appointing Michael Spindler as the chief operating officer . Gassée left the company later that year to set up a rival , Be Inc.", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG"]}, {"raw_text": "The company pivoted strategy and , in October 1990 , introduced three lower - cost models : the Macintosh Classic , the Macintosh LC , and the Macintosh IIsi , all of which generated significant sales due to pent - up demand . In 1991 , Apple introduced the hugely successful PowerBook with a design that set the current shape for almost all modern laptops . The same year , Apple introduced System 7 , a major upgrade to the Macintosh operating system , adding color to the interface and introducing new networking capabilities .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The success of the lower - cost Macs and the PowerBook brought increasing revenue . For some time , Apple was doing very well , introducing fresh new products at increasing profits . The magazine MacAddict named the period between 1989 and 1991 as the \" first golden age \" of the Macintosh .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The success of lower - cost consumer Macs , especially the LC , cannibalized higher - priced machines . To address this , management introduced several new brands , selling largely identical machines at different price points , for different markets : the high - end Quadra series , the mid - range Centris series , and the consumer - marketed Performa series . This led to significant consumer confusion between so many models .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The United Nations ( UN ) is a global intergovernmental organization established by the signing of the UN Charter on 26 June 1945 with the articulated mission of maintaining international peace and security , to develop friendly relations among states , to promote international cooperation , and to serve as a centre for harmonizing the actions of states in achieving those goals .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The United Nations headquarters is located in New York City , with several other offices located in Geneva , Nairobi , Vienna , and The Hague . The UN comprises six principal organizations : the General Assembly , the Security Council , the Economic and Social Council , the International Court of Justice , the Secretariat , and the Trusteeship Council which , together with several specialized agencies and related agencies , make up the United Nations System . There are in total 193 member states and 2 observer states .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The UN has primarily focused on economic and social development , particularly during the wave of decolonization in the mid-20th century . The UN has been recognized as a leader of peace and human development , with many officers and agencies having been awarded the Nobel Peace Prize , but has also been criticized for perceived ineffectiveness , bias , and corruption .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "In the century prior to the UN 's creation , several international organizations such as the International Committee of the Red Cross were formed to ensure protection and assistance for victims of armed conflict and strife .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "During World War I , several major leaders , especially U.S. president Woodrow Wilson , advocated for a world body to guarantee peace . The winners of the war , the Allies , met to decide on formal peace terms at the Paris Peace Conference . The League of Nations was approved and started operations , but the United States never joined . On 10 January 1920 , the League of Nations formally came into being when the Covenant of the League of Nations , ratified by 42 nations in 1919 , took effect . The League Council acted as an executive body directing the Assembly 's business . It began with four permanent members — the United Kingdom , France , Italy , and Japan .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "After some limited successes and failures during the 1920s , the League proved ineffective in the 1930s , as it failed to act against the Japanese invasion of Manchuria in 1933.[citation needed ] Forty nations voted for Japan to withdraw from Manchuria but Japan voted against it and walked out of the League instead of withdrawing from Manchuria . It also failed to act against the Second Italo - Ethiopian War , after the appeal for international intervention by Ethiopian Emperor Haile Selassie I at Geneva in 1936 went with no avail , including when calls for economic sanctions against Italy failed . Italy and other nations left the League .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "When World War II broke out in 1939 , the League effectively closed down .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The first step towards the establishment of the United Nations was the Inter - Allied Conference in London that led to the Declaration of St James 's Palace on 12 June 1941 . By August 1941 , American President Franklin Roosevelt and British Prime Minister Winston Churchill had drafted the Atlantic Charter ; which defined goals for the post - war world . At the subsequent meeting of the Inter - Allied Council in London on 24 September 1941 , the eight governments in exile of countries under Axis occupation , together with the Soviet Union and representatives of the Free French Forces , unanimously adopted adherence to the common principles of policy set forth by Britain and the United States .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Roosevelt and Churchill met at the White House in December 1941 for the Arcadia Conference . Roosevelt is considered a founder of the UN , and coined the term United Nations to describe the Allied countries . Churchill accepted it , noting its use by Lord Byron . The text of the Declaration by United Nations was drafted on 29 December 1941 , by Roosevelt , Churchill , and Harry Hopkins . It incorporated Soviet suggestions but included no role for France . One major change from the Atlantic Charter was the addition of a provision for religious freedom , which Stalin approved after Roosevelt insisted .", "gold_annotations": ["B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Roosevelt 's idea of the \" Four Powers \" , refers to the four major Allied countries , the United States , the United Kingdom , the Soviet Union , and China , emerged in the Declaration by the United Nations . On New Year 's Day 1942 , Roosevelt , Churchill , the Soviet Union 's former Foreign Minister Maxim Litvinov , and the Chinese Premier T. V. Soong signed the \" Declaration by United Nations \" , and the next day the representatives of twenty - two other nations added their signatures . During the war , the United Nations became the official term for the Allies . In order to join , countries had to sign the Declaration and declare war on the Axis powers .", "gold_annotations": ["B-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The October 1943 Moscow Conference resulted in the Moscow Declarations , including the Four Power Declaration on General Security . This declaration was signed by the Allied Big Four — the United States , the Soviet Union , the United Kingdom , and China — and aimed for the creation \" at the earliest possible date of a general international organization \" . This was the first public announcement that a new international organization was being contemplated to replace the League of Nations . The Tehran Conference followed shortly afterwards at which Roosevelt , Churchill and Joseph Stalin , the leader of the Soviet Union , met and discussed the idea of a post - war international organization.[citation needed ]", "gold_annotations": ["O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The new international organization was formulated and negotiated amongst the delegations from the Allied Big Four at the Dumbarton Oaks Conference from 21 September to 7 October 1944 . They agreed on proposals for the aims , structure and functioning of the new organization . It took the conference at Yalta in February 1945 , and further negotiations with the Soviet Union , before all the issues were resolved .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "By 1 March 1945 , 21 additional states had signed the Declaration by the United Nations . After months of planning , the UN Conference on International Organization opened in San Francisco on 25 April 1945 . It was attended by 50 nations ' governments and a number of non - governmental organizations . The delegations of the Big Four chaired the plenary meetings . Previously , Churchill had urged Roosevelt to restore France to its status of a major power after the liberation of Paris in August 1944 . The drafting of the Charter of the United Nations was completed over the following two months , and it was signed on 26 June 1945 by the representatives of the 50 countries . The UN officially came into existence at 20:07 ( UTC ) on 24 October 1945 , upon ratification of the Charter by the five permanent members of the Security Council : the United States , the United Kingdom , France , the Soviet Union and China — and by a majority of the other 46 nations .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The first meetings of the General Assembly , with 51 nations represented,[b ] and the Security Council took place in London beginning in January 1946 . Debates began at once , covering topical issues such as the presence of Russian troops in Iranian Azerbaijan and British forces in Greece . British diplomat Gladwyn Jebb served as interim secretary - general .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "The General Assembly selected New York City as the site for the headquarters of the UN . Construction began on 14 September 1948 and the facility was completed on 9 October 1952 . The Norwegian Foreign Minister , Trygve Lie , was the first elected UN secretary - general .", "gold_annotations": ["B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "Though the UN 's primary mandate was peacekeeping , the division between the United States and the Soviet Union often paralysed the organization ; generally allowing it to intervene only in conflicts distant from the Cold War . Two notable exceptions were a Security Council resolution on 7 July 1950 authorizing a US - led coalition to repel the North Korean invasion of South Korea , passed in the absence of the Soviet Union , and the signing of the Korean Armistice Agreement on 27 July 1953 .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "I-DATE", "I-DATE", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "On 29 November 1947 , the General Assembly approved Resolution 181 , a proposal to partition British Mandatory Palestine into two states , a Jewish state and an Arab state , with Jerusalem placed under international status . The Partition plan passed 33–13 with 10 abstentions and one absent . The plan was accepted by the Jews and rejected by the Arabs of Palestine and the Arab states leading to civil war . Following the declaration of the State of Israel on 15 May 1948 , the surrounding Arab armies invaded Palestine , beginning the 1948 Arab – Israeli War . Two years later , Ralph Bunche , a UN official , negotiated an armistice to the resulting conflict , with the Security Council deciding that \" an armistice shall be established in all sectors of Palestine \" . On 7 November 1956 , the first UN peacekeeping force was established to end the Suez Crisis ; however , the UN was unable to intervene against the Soviet Union 's simultaneous invasion of Hungary , following the country 's revolution .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "On 14 July 1960 , the UN established the United Nations Operation in the Congo ( or UNOC ) , the largest military force of its early decades , to bring order to Katanga , restoring it to the control of the Democratic Republic of the Congo by 11 May 1964 . While travelling to meet rebel leader Moise Tshombe during the conflict , Dag Hammarskjöld , often named as one of the UN 's most effective secretaries - general , died in a plane crash . Months later he was posthumously awarded the Nobel Peace Prize . In 1964 , Hammarskjöld 's successor , U Thant , deployed the UN Peacekeeping Force in Cyprus , which would become one of the UN 's longest - running peacekeeping missions .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-PERSON", "I-PERSON", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "With the spread of decolonization in the 1960s , the UN 's membership shot up due to an influx of newly independent nations . In 1960 alone , 17 new states joined the UN , 16 of them from Africa . On 25 October 1971 , with opposition from the United States , but with the support of many Third World nations , the People 's Republic of China was given the Chinese seat on the Security Council in place of the Republic of China ( also known as Taiwan ) . The vote was widely seen as a sign of waning American influence in the organization . Third World nations organized themselves into the Group of 77 under the leadership of Algeria , which briefly became a dominant power at the UN . On 10 November 1975 , a bloc comprising the Soviet Union and Third World nations passed a resolution , over strenuous American and Israeli opposition , declaring Zionism to be a form of racism . The resolution was repealed on 16 December 1991 , shortly after the end of the Cold War .", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-DATE", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "B-ORG", "I-ORG", "I-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O"]}, {"raw_text": "With an increasing Third World presence and the failure of UN mediation in conflicts in the Middle East , Vietnam , and Kashmir , the UN increasingly shifted its attention to its secondary goals of economic development and cultural exchange . By the 1970s , the UN budget for social and economic development was far greater than its peacekeeping budget.[citation needed ]", "gold_annotations": ["O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "I-LOC", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-LOC", "O", "O", "B-ORG", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O", "O",